this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - Radio net se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software
hello everyone welcome to software
engineering radio this is Felina and
today I have on the show with me the
Amelie Spinelli's he's a professor of
software engineering and the head of the
department of management science and
technology at the abscence University of
Economics and business until December he
served as the editor-in-chief of the I
Triple E software magazine yumminess is
also the author of the 2016 book
effective debugging and that's what we
will talk about on this show today the
aminos welcome to the show
it's my pleasure to be on the show so
the first question is debugging what
exactly is the bugging I feel this term
it's a little bit overloaded sometimes
people mean by debugging using a
debugger but sometimes people also just
mean finding or fixing a mistake
what is debugging to you exactly there
is overloaded but I think concentrating
on the debugger is a mistake in debug is
just a tool that's used in some specific
purposes it's not something that's the
most useful tool for debugging so I
would say that the bugging is a way to
quickly identify and fix a fault you can
use many different approaches for that
one of them is a debugger so something
like putting printf statements
everywhere you would say that is also
debugging it's definitely a debugging
method it's sometimes quite useful and
there are good arguments for putting
printf statements for example printf
statements in the code get maintained
with a code so they survive code changes
and refactorings and so on whereas if
you do something in the debugger if you
create a macro that might not survive
the code or it might only stay within
your system your fellow developers will
not see it that's actually a good point
as printf statements also serve as some
sort of mild documentation giving hints
to other developers that there some
debugging has taken place at that part
of the coast of course but for larger
systems you
to do it more systematically for example
using a logging framework think of
bunion for example for Java where you
have specific ways to enable/disable
statements and specify the level of a
verbosity in their logging yes so that's
like printf on steroids every framework
takes care of some more efficient ways
of handling things so in your book you
talked about different strategies for
debugging and we're already talking
about different strategies at this point
and you categorize these debugging
approaches in different groups you say
there are strategies and methods and
tools and techniques can you give the
listeners an overview of these different
categories of debugging approaches sure
when we talk about strategies these are
things that you can employ independently
of the problem for example one of my
favorite strategies is to look for on
the web for insights regarding the
problem so you if you see an error
message you might put it in double
quotes and search for that message and
you might encounter an answer that says
exactly why this has happened and how to
fix it there's nothing bad about it
looking at the how others have fixed a
problem you don't need to reinvent the
wheel or for example one other thing I
find useful is if I have a system that
used to work and doesn't work anymore to
see how these two things differ this can
apply to any type of problem or system
and this is why they I call them
high-level strategies you then talked
about the methods so these are specific
for these our target to specific
problems one thing I think is very
important is to make it to have to
enable the efficient reproduction of a
problem if it takes you 10 minutes to
reproduce a problem then it's very
difficult to fix it you can try things
and then have to if you have cycles of
10 minutes you proceed very slowly so if
you invest a bit of time nor to minimize
for example the input set or what types
of actions you need to perform the
program or automate them you know to
quickly reproduce it that's a very good
method in order to become more efficient
in debugging another practice I think is
important is once you are fixed
a narrowing your program to search for
similar error somewhere else and fix
them as well and then you also talked
about tools then of course the debugger
is one commonly used tools but there are
others that are less appreciated the
revision control system is one of them
so you may be using it for example and I
can talk more about that later or also
monitoring tools that allow you to see
how a specific program or process is
operating and am I correct in
understanding that these strategies and
metas are quite generic for all sorts of
programming language and systems but
that once we get to tools and techniques
they are a little bit more specific to
programming languages is that correct or
are there also tools and techniques that
work for any programming language in any
system your characters can move from
strategies to methods to specific tools
and techniques were becoming more
concrete and more specific to given
problems once that is you might even be
to sleep overnight for to solve a
problem you work on it and then you say
I give up you sleep overnight and may
often I found that in the next Mon you
have a solution in your head or if not a
solution a different debugging approach
so that's a strategy is not a specific
method or tool yeah that might even be a
good strategy for non computer science
related problems just going to sleep and
try it again the next day can you also
give an example of some tools and
techniques that are very specific to one
programming language and wouldn't really
work for another
yes for example there is a specific L
trace is a tool that allows you to
monitor calls to the C libraries this is
mostly useful when you're debugging C
and C++ programs and wouldn't be very
useful for other languages you will see
very low-level details in other
languages or you might want to monitor
packets flowing over the network this
again is used for networking
applications or for micro services and
not for applications that are monolithic
and we're ready talking about
programming languages a little bit and I
want to look at education of programming
languages because you mentioned these
tools that are only useful in a
certain setting for certain programming
language and I have this impression that
if people switch teams they go to
another team or even to another company
they know they have to learn a new
language if they go to a company where
they do Ruby development and oh I know I
have to learn Ruby but I think these
tools and techniques about debugging are
somewhat overlooked at a new skill that
people have to learn so how do people
learn about debugging how do you pick
this up
what are techniques for learning
debugging it's a very good question
because it's not typically formally
taught at the University and I think you
gain it through practice through
experience the most important way in
order to improve yourself and think is
interesting introspection so every time
you solve a problem you find a fault you
fix it think what worked well what
didn't work well what tools did you use
what tools would be useful in this case
and record them in your head or even a
notebook
so that you can apply them next time
also look at colleagues what are they
using what is do they find useful so
many different approaches and tools that
you need to always keep your eyes open
and they think of how you can improve
that's one reason I have devoted my book
to my mentors past and future I think we
can always constantly learn become
better at the debugging you think is
very interesting that you mentioned that
is very much learning on the job and I
have such impression as well that that
is the case but I'm not sure if that's
the most effective way for programming
we have this concept for example called
programming Coty's where you have really
tiny small programming puzzles that you
solve a bunch of times just so that you
get the techniques of the programming
language let's say in the fingers
wouldn't be more effective also with
debugging to test it to practice on
smaller examples rather than trying to
solve a big problem and then also have
some cognitive room in your brain left
to think about how what are the
strategies that I applies have you tried
any of these techniques to teach
programming or sorry to teach debugging
in a smaller scope
either in companies or winning the
university maybe I've
some instances by giving examples of
such methods or tools however one
problem is that in programming from
small even solving a small problem is
useful and you learn things in debugging
typically small a Fault in a small piece
of code is easy to find the difficulty
is if you have a system of millions of
lines of code and there is one line
there that's wrong that's the most
crucial difficulty and that's difficult
to teach through small examples that's
why on-the-job training or through
learning through experience is important
in debugging yeah examples are so
trivial to find the bug that it doesn't
really practice the skill well enough
hmm so you mentioned a little bit that
universities typically don't teach
debugging but but shouldn't they or
shouldn't we because the both of us are
so friends and your professors shouldn't
we teach debugging or do you say no this
is a skill that doesn't really fit a
programming education this is purely
something that industry should shoot
address we definitely should be teaching
debugging I think we teach debugging by
giving the students non-trivial
exercises any program larger than a few
lines will have bugs in it and students
or professionals in then after they
graduate we'll need to expend time in
order to find those problems those
errors and fix them so by that you learn
how to debug more formally I think that
we should teach our students how to use
a debugger what other tools that can use
different approaches that can apply to
problems yeah I don't think when I was
in university that they taught me how to
learn in debugger this is really a skill
you just pick up in programming projects
sort of by yourself but that might not
be the best the best strategy so do you
do this in classes do you teach classes
where you show people how to use a
debugger we talked about the debugging
tools and we have laboratory sessions
where they use for example Eclipse and
learn how to apply clips no to single
step through a program or look at
variables at the breakpoints and so on
these are the most important functions
of a debugger and I want to talk about
assessment also a little bit both in the
context of a university course but also
in terms of record
because many companies if they want to
recruit programmers they do whiteboard
interviews where they test if people can
program at least in this setting but I
haven't heard of many companies that
typically assess if people can use a
debugger if they can find bugs do you
think this is a practice that is common
and or should it be common it should be
it should be something that is assessed
I think it can be assessed through a
discussion so you can give a candidate a
given problem and discuss how the
candidate would approach that problem an
application is not responding or their
application crashes how would the
candidate approach that problem and
through that discussion you can quickly
find out where the candidate knows how
to handle such problems or has
experience with that or not that's a
good strategy just talk to a problem not
just have them debug specifically but
just talk about approaches I like that
as a strategy I want to talk also a
little bit about the workflow of
debugging because if people are
debugging they're often also involved in
other activities like testing and
refactoring it's very rare that you just
fake a fix a bug and you're not looking
at other parts of the code so maybe can
you describe what your ideal flow of a
debugging process would be where do you
start
when you when you know you're finished
mmm yeah sure so the first place to
start would be to affect efficiently
reproduce the problem we talked about
that earlier find the minimum working
example that demonstrates the problem
and through that you can find also the
fault then you need to locate exactly
where the fault is once you have
isolated the failure there are various
methods to do that you can drill up or
down so start from the manifestation of
the problem and try to find the line
where it occurs or drill up so you have
a specific line where you know that your
program crashes through an exception or
something similar and wrong output and a
wrong result and you want to drill up to
find out where why this problem has
occurred both are valid strategies and
there are different times where each one
is more useful
then the other once you have identified
what was wrong in the problem of course
you need to fix it and then also comes
some housekeeping so that would involve
first of all looking for other instances
of the same problem and fixing those as
well
ensuring that this doesn't happen in the
future perhaps for some refactoring or
some additional documentation or the
addition of some assertions and also
communicating the problem to your group
your team so you have an issue you need
to close it you may need if it was a big
problem you may need to conduct the
post-mortem and discuss it with your
colleagues and so on and miss this
process always the same do you have the
same flow for all sorts of different
types of bugs because I can imagine a
security bug is really very different
from a performance issue does this
strategy always hold or are the
different workflows for different types
of issues there are in the different
workflows so you mentioned performance
this has a very different workflows has
to do with measurement understanding
what the type of problem you're
witnessing is is your system IO bound is
it waiting a lot of time for packets to
arrive from the network or from blocks
to be read from the disk is it CPU bound
is it time your processor and if that is
the case is the processor executing some
code on your behalf or is it executing
code within the operating system context
and then drilling down or to find out
hotspot areas if it's CPU bound specific
functions or even lines of code where
the program is taking a lot of time you
would then use some strategy know to
improve the performance of your problem
for example through a more efficient
algorithm or by using a better data
structure or even by a look by removing
many calls to the operating system and
then you would measure again in order to
see whether you have fixed that
performance problem or not okay
fixing bugs is always risky right there
are many cases known maybe you have a
few examples where people
fix one bug but introduced another bug
in another part of the system how do you
lower the risk of debugging and bug
fixing it is risky but not as risky as a
refactoring where you start with a
working system and you aim to give back
a working system again in debugging you
start with a system that has a fault in
it and a system that has failed and you
need to fix that so it's typically you
will give a system that's a bit better
than the system that you started with
how do you lower the risk the answer is
easy you need to have to you need to
test the system ideally you should have
unit tests integration tests and so on
that can assert that at the end of your
session your system is working as it was
whereas it worked before here it's
important before you start to fix that
to fix the system to add an additional
test that demonstrates the failure that
you are trying to address so that once
you have fixed the fault the system will
pass that test as well and also as an
additional bonus if that fault is
introduced in the future the test will
catch it yeah so you're not just fixing
the bug now but you're also trying to
make sure that the bug doesn't happen or
similar bugs doesn't have don't happen
in the future
mm-hmm and that you know that you have
actually fixed the bug you can
demonstrate it that the fact that the
bug has been fixed so I really enjoyed
reading your book if the strategies are
very very useful but I found here and
there it goes a bit beyond debugging
maybe for example some of the some of
the strategies you mentioned are very
much about code comprehension
for example item 47 says write your code
in a different programming language to
gain a deeper understanding of what is
happening or 66 rewrite your code at a
higher level of abstraction I would say
those are all most strategies just for
code comprehension for understanding the
code that would be useful also if I'm
starting to work on a new code base nose
even necessarily if there is a bug so I
guess my question is is code comprehend
and a big part of debugging and if so
how big mmm it depends on the problem so
some problems can be can be solved
rather easily just by looking at the
specific kind of the specific line of
your code you see a null dereference and
you understand that in the specific if
statement you need to first check that
the variable is not null before
accessing a method through it so that's
easy probably you don't need to
understand the whole codebase but there
are other problems that are quite deep
you are manipulating a complex data
structure and you need to obtain a
specific result and the result is
slightly wrong you have a an application
a card application and you have some
lines that intersect when they should
not intersect how do you deal with that
in that case if you have a complex
algorithm that you have developed
yourself it might be quite difficult to
isolate the problem maybe the problem is
not in a specific line but in the way
you manage the whole data structure or
you have understood the problem in this
case rephrasing the problem rewriting it
in a higher-level language might get rid
of many non-essential details and might
help you get a clearer picture of how to
approach the problem and where the
problem lies so if you are at the same
time trying to get correct the C
pointers and also understand a very
complex algorithm that is involves many
routines you might be doomed if you can
express it easier using Python sets for
example then you might understand the
problem better and you either keep it in
that higher-level language or rewrite it
again correctly in the lower level
language that it was initially
implemented in yeah so you're saying
that sometimes it is useful to rewrite
the code in different way but not not in
all situations could you also give an
example in a minority it's useful in a
minority of situations who are dealing
with very complex algorithms and you
cannot fix them and understanding their
language they're written in it's not a
common approach but sometimes it is
useful yeah so you're saying it's the
minority of cases in most of the
situations this would not be a viable
strategy is key it's mainly algorithmic
problems okay
you also mention automation quite a bit
in your book one of your tips is even
also makes debugging tasks he is
debugging is a big part of debugging
automating the process there's a larger
element in it especially for non-trivial
problems so in some in one instance I
had a problem where I needed to the
specific language responding a specific
function was responding very slowly but
the input that it was getting was quite
complex so the way I solve it was to
write a small script that's broke the
input into parts and gave to the
function each small part in series until
I found a specific part of the input
that was making the function respond
very slowly so toe motion can help you
in a number of cases where you're
dealing with complex inputs and
non-trivial processes it allows you to
drill down and find out what parts are
responsible for a failure B could you
also give an example where automation
would not really help
are there specific types of problems
where you say well maybe the automation
would get in the way if understanding
would be better to do it as manually as
possible or is automation always good
Automation is good when you're dealing
with complex input or complex tasks that
are cumbersome to do manually if the
problem screams at you if you have an
exception in a specific line often you
don't need the automation but if you
have a 100 megabyte log file and you
need to find out which line was
responsible for the failure you are
seeing maybe automating the process of
filtering that log file feeding your
program with specific instances of lines
that were associated with the problem
can help you quickly arrive at the
source of the fault so it's a matter of
scale as well the larger problem or the
larger your code base the more important
automation gets the code base and also
the data you are handling you maybe have
a small code base but huge amount of
data which you need to process autum in
some
- fashioned automatically in order to
arrive at the ones that are associated
with a failure we already talked a
little bit about programming languages
and different strategies and I want to
zoom into that a little bit more because
while reading your book I thought maybe
it's the case that some strategies don't
fit all programming paradigms do you
agree with me are there some strategies
that are a little bit more specific
towards a certain programming paradigm I
can give an example for example your
rule 33 is examined that values of
variables if you work in a purely
functional programming language there
are no very variable so there's nothing
to inspect so that rule doesn't really
help do you agree with me that some of
the parrot some programming paradigms
fit really well with some strategies but
not with others yes definitely some
approaches can work better with some
languages than others but again this is
not doesn't mean that they cannot be
used
you mentioned variables in functional
languages you often let variable have a
value but only once in a functional
language so inspecting that may be
helpful or other languages don't have
good debuggers associated with them or
their debuggers that are cumbersome to
use so it's easier to do to add logging
or printf statements for them so it all
what's that the G is most effective
really depends on the language and the
tools that are associated with it and
how would you know this how do you know
what strategies fits what programming
paradigm is this again just a matter of
experience or is there some sort of
classification that people could read
this experience because also things
change a new tool comes out that's very
useful for a specific language and it's
also a matter of learning the best tools
for for a specific language so looking
around find and always trying to improve
yourself one important element is when
you see yourself toiling needlessly to
know to find a fault to think how could
I do this better and invest in learning
a new tool in a new method rather than
trying the a process that's cumbersome
again the gained again if you don't
prove yourself then you will never
become an effective debugger yes you
also need metacognitive skills to think
Hey am i doing the right thing here is
this a good strategy if I'm doing the
same thing for three hours or if I'm the
debugging the same type of problem every
week then maybe I need a better strategy
exactly so you might be using a strategy
that allows you to find the source of
the problem but you also need always to
think how could I have done this better
yes also general good advice in every
situation look back and what was a good
strategy here what was helpful and where
could I have been more effective I also
want to talk a little bit about newer
programming paradigms because when I was
in university debugging was relatively
easy because I ran a program on my
machine and was relatively small so in
debugger was very useful but for example
now we have big website systems with
front end and a back end that maybe a
model-view-controller system that I'm
not directly executing all the code that
I am working with does that affects how
we do debugging do do we as feel do
debugging way differently on the web
then on the back end or do you say well
the big strategies are more or less the
same it doesn't really matter if it's a
combination of different types of
systems and languages the biggest are
just always work but when you want to
use concrete methods and tools then
these things change so for the systems
that you describe you need to have a
holistic view of the system to know all
the parts of it and how they fit
together what is executed at the
database level
what's executed on the client what's
executed on the server how these fit
together what the API is and how you can
put monitoring how you can have more how
you can monitor interactions between
those elements
you already mentioned a holistic view of
a whole system which is of course a very
very great strategy but what if your
code depends heavily on libraries then
it gets harder maybe to have a full view
of what the system is doing because you
haven't created all parts of the system
and you might not have a deep
understanding of what
you are depending on what if you have to
be back that's right what do you do with
libraries one ways to monitor the
interaction with the library to see if
what you are sending to the library
matches what it is expecting and what
you are getting back much is what you
are expecting to receive and another
thing that's often not done is to
actually simply step into the library so
having the source code of the library
which is often possible nowadays either
because the library is open source or
because the vendors supply source code
with the libraries that you didn't this
wasn't the case often in the past it
allows you to go into the library and
see what the library is doing and by
simply stepping with a debugger through
the libraries code you can often
understand much better how the library
is handling something and you can either
identify a misunderstanding from your
part how the library is operating or
actually see a bug within the library
which you can then sidestep or ask the
vendor to fix and if we take such a
system one step further if we're not
talking about one big system with a few
libraries but we're talking about an
architecture of microservices does that
impact debugging how do you debug a
system that has many separate components
it's definitely trickier that's where
there is a saying that if you cannot
handle something as a monolithic block
how can you expect it to work with it as
a and D compositing to microservices
here you definitely need the login at
the all levels and by all micro services
you need better instrumentation in order
to be able to reenact specific failures
that you have seen from the form it was
logged so that you can identify which
microservice failed and why it failed
yes the first choice is maybe how do we
break up the system and then we try to
debug the smaller parts and then debug
the whole is that is that in summary you
need to be able to understand how the
whole is working through logging and
then replay that logging in order to
find out the specific fault yes sorry
identify the smallest part of your
system when error occurred debug it in
the smallest scope possible that sends
in mind
different from a big system with a bunch
of libraries because then also the same
question is where does the bug occur
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software the customers
love digitalocean stands out from the
crowd due to its simplicity high
performance and no billing surprises
join a community of over 3.5 million
developers on digitalocean sign up with
a free credit at doco slash se radio do
you think that as a field if we take all
software engineers or programmers
together
are we getting better at debugging what
big advances have you seen in debugging
in practice we certainly have more
powerful tools nowadays for example now
there are debugger that allow you to
step back in time this is magical it
couldn't happen a decade ago this tools
work by recording every instruction that
the processor takes in memory the side
effects of it and allowing you to go
back because we have plentiful memory
and very powerful processors that allow
you to do that this is magic I often
find myself at the specific point
realizing ah the fault was earlier how
can I now go back with back in time
debugging you can actually do that and
step through your code backward so this
is a big improvement and we have other
old tools that allow us make our life
easier one other one of my another thing
that I find extremely useful is data
breakpoints you can specify that you
want your code to break when a specific
value changes this is a lot more
difficult than code break points because
code breakpoints are simply implemented
by adding by putting a simple interrupt
instruction at the point where you want
the go your code to stop data
breakpoints need the processor to
monitor all data accesses to find out
when specific value changes modern
processors have specific hardware
in order to do this and this allows us
to have this debugging capability heard
you say when this variable changes I
don't care where needed where the
corresponding code is I want my program
to break I found many bugs with this way
and I think this is a big improvement
compared to what was the case years ago
on the other hand sometimes people are
becoming lazy because you have all these
possibilities people are concentrating
less on writing programs correct or
identifying bugs on paper or on a
listing like they want to use
interactive tools in order to find the
bug I think think this is fine because
we have this tool you have these
capabilities so why not use them so in
general getting better because the tools
are more powerful and that might come at
the expense of people working with tools
rather than let's say look out of the
window and think a lots but that isn't
because the tools are so strong that
it's worth it to make the developers a
bit lazy that's that's more or less a
summary right exactly and through that
we're building much bigger systems so
yes maybe we're getting laser and they'd
find errors in ten lines of code because
we can fire the bugger and find it for
us but we are not building systems with
ten lines of code but ten million lines
of code and you're saying parts of the
responsibility for being able to build
bigger system is because we're so much
better and debugging and and without
that back in time debugging or these
data points we wouldn't have been able
maybe to build such braces through such
big systems with all the tools that we
have all the thought let me let me do
that again the tools that we have I
wouldn't isolate back in time debugging
because it's something that's currently
evolving it's not something that's
universally used allow us to create much
more complex systems yeah in general not
just debugging tools but all sorts of
tools of course let's step the topic of
tools a little bit you also mentioned
this earlier in your interview and I
want to get back to this now you said
gates or version control systems are
also very important tools of debugging
I don't immediately see how these things
relate to each other so could you
Reitan what does a version control
system have to do with debugging
absolutely I would think that about the
fifth the fourth of the problems I'm
investigating and fix him I'm using a
version control system know to help me
debug the problem how do I do that first
of all I run get blame in order to see
who changed the line that I think is a
bit iffy so maybe that line was changed
ten years ago or last week the third two
things are very different was changed
ten years ago probably the problem is
not in that line if was changed last
week maybe a fellow developer introduced
or maybe even I introduced fault in that
line another way that the version
control system can help you is if you
have an older version of the system that
works and the newer that doesn't work
you can identify which change brought to
that problem there is even a specific
tip command git bisect that allows you
to find exactly which version introduced
the problem there may be 100 versions
between the version that worked and the
version where the problem was identified
git bisect will cut that number to 50
then to 25 then to 12 and so on until
that dent if I see exactly the version
where the problem manifests itself I
think this is extremely useful because
you have narrowed down maybe 2,000 lines
of changes into 15 lines that were
changed between the two versions that
brought on the problem to you these same
amazing tools in need to use compare in
collaboration with debugging tools do
you think this is common practice to
many people in practice use kids for
debugging I've seen it happening I think
experienced developers certainly do it
but these are things that we must become
aware of and learn that's why I wrote
the book for a number of years I was
writing small notes for every debugging
practice method tool that I used and to
try to systematize them so that people
become aware of them and use them
because I don't think that this
knowledge gained through decades of
experience is accessible to all no I
definitely agree I don't think my first
intuition would be to use a version
control system I'm still very much in
this
mode of the debugger so I really learned
a lot from your book you also mentioned
earlier in the show but also in the book
that monitoring can be an important tool
for debugging can you elaborate on that
- what do we have here nowadays we have
very complex systems not a monolithic
system but something that depends that
runs on multiple CPUs computers even
data centers across the world so when a
problem happens you need to find out
when it happened why it happened was
what was going on at that time for that
you need to have good monitoring so find
out which processes respond how long
they take to respond when they stopped
responding what they were doing at that
time so being able to see the status of
your processes and log all the actions
that happened will help you identify the
problem so nowadays where don't
debugging is not only the task of
finding a problem in a specific line of
code but identifying a failing process
or a process that's responding slowly or
a process that sometimes fails these are
different skills and different require
different strategies than identifying
specific lines of code so if I
understand you correctly a monitoring
system can tell you hey this service is
very slow or there might be an issue
there which I understand as support for
being aware that there is a bug but how
does a monitoring system help you to fix
a bug you said earlier that modern
systems and I agree with that are
composed of many processes so the bug
may be completely unrelated to the
problem that you see in the process
being monitored some user somewhere sees
a wrong number in a webpage but many
levels beneath you might see that the
process is taking a lot of time to
respond or is not responding at all so
if you have a complex system being able
to monitor and see what each process is
doing how it is behaving will allow you
to isolate and complex bug that
manifests itself in a very different
part of your organization yeah so it's
again more about gaining a deep
understanding of the Sheppard's LM
of your system and how they work
together and monitoring is a tool that
can help you understand how everything
in the system is working together
exactly often in modern systems you see
one webpage and beneath it hundreds of
microservices have executed in order to
produce that page if you see a problem
in that page without knowing how all
those things worked together it's very
difficult to isolate it and fix it yes I
think I can summarize that as that
monitoring is also a tool for
comprehension of the running system no
necessary code comprehension in terms of
reading a bunch of lines of code but
more getting an understanding of how
everything is going exactly nowadays we
don't debug isolated systems often with
the bug complex systems of systems and
for that we need to have an
understanding of how all parts work
together very clear I want to talk a
little bit about this new mode so in
software developer in May mainly in
Silicon Valley where some companies say
it's very important to just move fast
and break things and we'll deal with the
consequences later how does that relate
to debugging is this maybe maybe also a
response to the fact that the buggers
are so good and we're able to find bugs
very quickly true monitoring into
version control systems that aren't are
we less worried about bugs and is this
why something like new fast and break
things can really gain traction there
are many reasons for moving fast and
breaking things but the ability to
efficiently debug what you have broken
is one one reason why this can work
so if failure is expensive in terms of
the consequences and how you can deal
with it and how you can debug it then of
course you cannot move fast and break
things and gain the efficiency that this
might give you if you can quickly
isolate the problem then move fast and
break things is helpful so let me give
you a concrete example think of a system
call you need to do some refactoring and
you are not exactly sure what effect
this will have after the refactoring you
can try to compile it and maybe the
compiler will give you errors in lines
that don't match
is expected so that's one failure that
allows you to quickly identify what
other things you needed to fix you can
run the system the system fails on some
assertions or crashes and gives you
specific lands that crashed again you
can quickly if you have the appropriate
instrumentation and tools you can
quickly go to those lines and fix them
if you have good test coverage this will
identify most lines that were affected
and this makes it easy for you to
experiment and move fast because you
know that you can quickly then fix and
identify and fix the problems that have
been introduced yes so it's partly due
to debugging because or maybe mainly due
to monitoring because you can find
issues and quickly address them and also
one thing you mentioned of course that
failure shouldn't be too expensive it's
probably not a good strategy to apply
move fast and break things if you're
building a spaceship or something
because if you made a type it will be
too expensive
exactly that case is where this applies
in cases where this shouldn't apply I
don't want to talk about risk a little
bit more we talked about that in
beginning of the show as well you said
well to lower the risk of debugging
operations testing is a really good
strategy so I want to talk about this
intersection between debugging and
testing firstly there is this concept of
testable code of code is very modular
and it's easy to test is there a similar
concept that you can say well this code
is very debuggable is that a thing or is
testable code also always debuggable
code any other way around right so
testable code is also debuggable code
but there are additional things we can
do in order to make code easy to debug
let me give you two examples one is when
a function returns a specific value
through a return statement then it's
difficult to see what the function has
returned especially if it's directly
used by another function that has called
it so by assigning that value to a
variable and then returning the value of
that variable this makes it easier to
understand what the function has
returned otherwise you might resort to
low-level the
such as looking at the values of the
register where the value has returned
its value
another example is complex statements
that are composite and have many
different conditions boolean ands and
ORS and so on
again this is difficult to see which one
of them has specific value and why a
complex boolean expression results in an
if statement being taken or not if this
is broken down to smaller expressions
that you can step through and look with
your debugger this makes your life
easier
so there are some differences you say
between testable code and debuggable
code because if I may summarize her
answer the examples you gave I think
have to do with breaking the code up in
small steps don't nest a lot of
operations don't make very complex
boolean operations but split it into
smaller steps so it's easier to see
where the issue occurs that might be the
general strategy you're describing you
write yes you need to be able to
identify both the flow in the code and
also the values in the code and if we
are testing so suppose everyone takes
your advice they go debugging but first
they add some tests what type of tests
are we talking about do you mean unit
tests do you mean integration tests what
type of tests supports debugging in
general it depends on the problem and
the fault that you are trying to address
so if it's a complex a failure then you
might need an integration test in order
to see it but once you have narrowed
down the specific method then a unit
test might be able to identify it and
show demonstrate that you have corrected
it so it very much depends on the
situation is what you're saying exactly
yes then let's talk about test code I
have often maybe I'm the only one but I
have often encountered a situation where
I was be bugging for a very very long
time and I couldn't fix the bug and it
turned out there was a bug in my test
code how do we deal with that how do we
debug test code is debugging test code
different
debugging regular code do the same
strategies apply or are there different
strategies it's the same as debugging
regular code with the advantage that you
narrow down very much what you're trying
to fix because you have an intimate
coupling between the code that you check
and the testing code so I think most
cases quite easy to debug test code or
the code that is being tested in my
experience I'm always very thankful when
I write unit tests that a specific
problem was identified by the unit test
and I didn't have to wait to see it in
production through some obscure example
so in a sense you're saying test
debugging test code might be easier
because you've already narrowed down the
place of the bug so it's easier to debug
because the scope already is pretty
small yes and we're always lucky when we
identify problems at this level of scope
it's much better to find the problem
when testing rather than when a customer
responds with an obscure failure case
before we close the show I want to talk
about one specific issue in debugging
that that happens when we program in one
programming language but with debug in
another programming language nowadays
there are many programming languages
that compile to JavaScript for example
type Cribs
so you program type scripts but often
the debugger runs on the JavaScript
level so you have these two levels for
your programming and debugging on two
different levels so to speak do you have
any advice for that specific situation
yes the advice here is to become
intimately familiar with the lung the
target language it's typically not very
difficult and it's a very valuable skill
I've we often have systems that compile
from one language to another sometimes
it takes time for debuggers to to get to
support the higher-level language and
until that time happens we need to
become familiar with a lower level
language where the program is developed
is compiled into
and this doesn't only happen with the
JavaScript as you give us an example a
very common case is when we are dealing
with the mushroom assembly machine
language of where the code is the but
this is a very valuable skill assembly
code is not something obscure and
magical it takes a little bit of reading
and practice not to understand it and
being able to single step through the
compiled code is very valuable very
valuable skill and sometimes something
very useful you see a statement you
execute it and you don't understand why
it works in specific way you switch to
assembly language view or to JavaScript
as you mentioned and you see that as
compiled to something that you weren't
expecting it to compile into you maybe
you've forgotten a semicolon or
misplaced the bracket and the precedence
is wrong or it has happened to me at
least twice in my life there was a
compiler bug that generated wrong code
so being able to see the lower-level
code not being afraid to do that is a
very variable skill so until debuggers
are good enough to completely operate at
a higher level at the typescript level
for example we cannot get rid of the
lower level language the target language
because in some cases you would still
need to be able to debug at a lower
level right exactly for difficult
problems and experts people who debug
code they will need to do it at the very
least for the people who write the
compilers from the high level language
to the lower level one now that's nuts
may be a bit sad because maybe some
people want to rather program and debug
at the higher level but it makes total
sense that until they're perfect we
really also need to understand the
target level as a professional it makes
you more valuable engine wants to be in
that place true is there anything you
want to add to the show
anything we didn't cover about debugging
that you feel very passionate about the
issue of tools we talked about
automation what I think is very
important is to get yourself the
knowledge and the skills in order to
automate things with specific tools one
category could be a scripting language
so being proficient in say PI
in order to automate how you deal with
data how you process long log files it
can be one way to deal with that another
would be to use UNIX tools on the
command line so no to grab quickly
through a source code base to identify
where a specific division is taking
place so that you can fix it it's a very
valuable skill any other skills that you
think or tools that you think are really
valuable for debugging or maybe even in
general yes thank you for asking that
tracing tools so there is a category of
tools such as S Trace that allows you to
see how your process is interacting with
the operating system if you are sent
back on a desert island that allowed me
to take only one tool with me I would
take s trace rather than say debugger
because whatever happens in an
application it's usually through
interactions with the operating system
by monitoring this interaction see what
files it opens what it reads from a file
what it writes what data sends to other
processes what memory it allocates you
can get a very good picture of how the
process is operating so if you are not
using s trace the trace system DUP and
so on get to know these tools and apply
them to problems that you may have okay
what one final question at the close of
the show your book has has a lot of tips
and tools and strategies but maybe you
can share your favorite one if we just
get one strategy from the entire book
what is your absolute favorite gives
your software's debugging facilities so
complex systems have built-in debugging
facilities this could be logging this
could be operating on on the foreground
rather than as a daemon this could be
giving you access to internal state this
often allows you to understand problems
better especially in complex systems if
you are dealing with systems of millions
of lines of code debugger often doesn't
cut it that's why this is have their own
debugging facilities and by using them
you can become a better debugger so
important summary there maybe is the
tools you work with
you have to deeply understand them and
have to know the capabilities of the
tools you work with to use them in the
most powerful way their systems that you
are debugging yes the systems that your
about me and not even necessarily
programming tools but maybe the
operating system or a processor that you
work on learnt a database that you work
with stuff like that right exactly you
mentioned a database or databases
availability to log the simple
statements they're executing and to
explain to you how they process a
specific query what the indexes they are
using and so on so debugging a
performance problem without using these
facilities is like trying to walk in the
dark in the dark maze that's really good
advice of course we already mentioned
the book we'll put a link to the book in
the show notes but are there any other
places the amoenus where people can
follow you or read about the work that
you do I tweet through cool s/w engg
cool software engineering cool Swank I
also have a blog where people can where
I occasionally blog about problems I
find in solutions I like and I have a
github account where I put this is that
I put this at code I develop that's this
Bonelli's on github ok we'll make sure
that all of those are attitude to show
notes so people can easily find you and
read about all the exciting things
you're working on thanks a lot for being
on the show today thank you very much
for having me thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening